<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="ludovicc@users.sourceforge.net">Ludovic
    Claude</author>

    <title>CVSGrab - Read sources stored in CVS behind a
    firewall</title>
  </properties>

  <meta name="KeyWords"
  content="WinCvs, cvs, MacCvs, gCvs, jCVS, firewall, proxy, retrieve cvs tree, grab, behind, checkout" />

  <body>
    <section name="What it is:">
      <p>People often complain that they cannot checkout files from
      a public CVS repository because they are behind a corporate
      firewall that blocks access to the pserver. The standard
      workaround, use ssh, works only for registered users, not
      anonymous users. Some firewall support also http tunelling,
      where access to the pserver is possible with a standard CVS
      client, but unfortunately it is not used in all organisations
      (or even for personal firewalls).</p>

      <p>CVSGrab is another kind of CVS client. When other CVS
      clients use the cvs protocol or ssh to read the repository,
      this utility reads the repository via its ViewCVS web
      interface.</p>

      <p>The advantage is that if you are behind a firewall that
      prevents you from updating files from a remote CVS server,
      this program will be able to bypass the firewall and download
      the latest files from the repository.</p>

      <p>Disadvantages are that you have only read access to the
      repository, the repository needs to be public and have
      ViewCVS set up. 
      <br />

      Also, it adds a more important load on the web server, so try
      to use this tool reasonably.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="How it works:">
      <p>CVSGrab can be started either from the command line or
      from an Ant task.</p>

      <p>It starts by reading the top page of the ViewCVS
      repository, then parses the links in this page and browses
      all the pages bellow while downloading the files in them.</p>

      <p>In addition, the CVS administration files (the files under
      the Cvs folder present on every directory) are created and
      store the version number for each files. The next time you
      run CVSGrab, those version numbers are used to download only
      the files that have being updated.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="Tested with:">
      <p>
        <ul>
          <li>ViewCVS 0.7 on 
          <a href="http://www.eclipse.org">www.eclipse.org</a>
          </li>

          <li>ViewCVS 0.8 on 
          <a href="http://www.sourceforge.net">Sourceforge.net</a>
          </li>

          <li>ViewCVS 0.9.2 on 
          <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org">jakarta.apache.org
          (some time ago...)</a>
          </li>

          <li>ViewCVS 1.0-dev on 
          <a href="http://www.picocontainer.org">
          www.picocontainer.org</a>

          , 
          <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org">
          jakarta.apache.org</a>

          and 
          <a href="http://savannah.gnu.org">savannah.gnu.org</a>
          </li>

          <li>SourceCast 1.0 on 
          <a href="http://www.netbeans.org">www.netbeans.org</a>
          </li>

          <li>SourceCast 2.0 on 
          <a href="http://dev.java.net">dev.java.net</a>
          </li>

          <li>CvsWeb 1.0 on 
          <a href="http://dev.w3.org/cvsweb/">dev.w3.org</a>
          </li>
          
          <li>CvsWeb 2.0 on 
          <a href="http://www.kde.org/">www.kde.org</a>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>

      <p>Author: Ludovic Claude ( 
      <a href="mailto:ludovicc at users.sourceforge.net">email</a>

      ), freelance developer</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>

