<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="ludovicc@users.sourceforge.net">Ludovic
    Claude</author>

    <title>CVSGrab - Read sources stored in CVS behind a
    firewall</title>
  </properties>

  <meta name="KeyWords"
  content="WinCvs, cvs, MacCvs, gCvs, jCVS, firewall, proxy, retrieve cvs tree, grab, behind, checkout" />

  <body>
    <section name="What it is:">
      <p>People often complain that they cannot checkout files from
      a public CVS repository because they are behind a corporate
      firewall that blocks access to the pserver. The standard
      workaround, use ssh, works only for registered users, not
      anonymous users. Some firewall support also http tunelling,
      where access to the pserver is possible with a standard CVS
      client, but unfortunately it is not used or allowed in all organisations
      (or even with personal firewalls).</p>

      <p>CVSGrab is another kind of CVS client. When other CVS
      clients use the cvs protocol or ssh to read the repository,
      this utility reads the repository via its web
      interface, such as ViewCVS or CvsWeb.</p>

      <p>The advantage is that if you are behind a firewall that
      prevents you from updating files from a remote CVS server,
      this program will be able to bypass the firewall and download
      the latest files from the repository.</p>

      <p>Disadvantages are that you have only read access to the
      repository, the repository needs to be public and have
      ViewCVS set up. 
      <br />

      Also, it adds a more important load on the web server, so try
      to use this tool reasonably.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="How it works:">
      <p>CVSGrab can be started either from the command line or
      from an Ant task.</p>

      <p>It starts by reading the top page of the ViewCVS
      repository, then parses the links in this page and browses
      all the pages below while downloading the files in them.</p>

      <p>In addition, the CVS administration files (the files under
      the Cvs folder present on every directory) are created and
      store the version number for each files. The next time you
      run CVSGrab, those version numbers are used to download only
      the files that have being updated.</p>
    </section>

    <section name="New and Cool">
      <section name="New url parameter (starting version 2.2)"> 
        <p>The detection of web interfaces has been improved, and now to start cvsgrab,
          you need only to give the full url of the web repository to download.</p>
          
        <p>For example, to download the latest version of Ant in its 1.6 branch, you may use only</p>
        <code>
          cvsgrab -url http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/ant/?only_with_tag=ANT_16_BRANCH
        </code>
        <p>
          This is much simpler, the -rootUrl, -packagePath, -versionTag and -cvsroot parameters are now optional. <br/>
          But sometimes the autodetection may fail, so it's still possible to use the old style:
        </p>
        <code>
          cvsgrab -rootUrl http://cvs.apache.org/viewcvs.cgi/ -packagePath ant -tag ANT_16_BRANCH
        </code>
      </section>
      <section name="Diff functionality (starting version 2.1)"> 
        <p>Now you can create a patch file when you modify source code that has 
            been checked out with CVSGrab.</p>
          
        <p>For that, run <b>cvsgrab -diff</b> from your project root, and a file
            called patch.txt is created that contains your modifications in the 
            unified patch format. The file is compatible with the command cvs diff -u
            that is the standard for submitting patches for most open source projects
            (see <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/source.html#Patches">Apache's guidelines</a>         
        </p>
      </section>
      <section name="Compatibility with standard cvs clients"> 
        <p>Let's suppose that you connect your notebook behind a firewall that blocks cvs.
          Now, you want to download the latest code from project X, which is still under development
          and with some blocking bugs in their latest release.          
        </p>
        <p>To check out files, you use cvsgrab with the -cvsRoot parameter. This parameter is the equivalent
          of the -d parameter on the cvs command. for example, if you use this command to check out files without a firewall: <br/>
          cvs -z3 -d:ext:developername@cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/cvsgrab co cvsgrab <br/>
          then the cvsgrab command to use should be: <br/>
          cvsgrab -cvsRoot :ext:developername@cvs.sourceforge.net:/cvsroot/cvsgrab -rootUrl http://cvs.sourceforge.net/viewcvs.py/ 
             -packagePath cvsgrab/cvsgrab -destDir c:/tmp -packageDir cvsgrab 
        </p>
        <p>You have fixed the bugs, and changed lots of source files. To submit your changes back to 
          project X, where you have write access, you connect your notebook to an internet connection with 
          no blocking firewall, then you use your preferred cvs client (command line, ViewCVS...) and commit
          your work directly, with no additional setup.
        </p>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section name="Tested with:">
      <p>
        <ul>
          <li><a href="http://viewcvs.sourceforge.net/">ViewCVS</a> 0.7 on 
          <a href="http://www.eclipse.org">www.eclipse.org</a>
          </li>

          <li><a href="http://viewcvs.sourceforge.net/">ViewCVS</a> 0.8 on 
          <a href="http://www.sourceforge.net">Sourceforge.net</a>
          </li>

          <li><a href="http://viewcvs.sourceforge.net/">ViewCVS</a> 0.9.2 on 
          <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org">jakarta.apache.org
          (some time ago...)</a>
          </li>

          <li><a href="http://viewcvs.sourceforge.net/">ViewCVS</a> 1.0-dev on 
          <a href="http://www.picocontainer.org">
          www.picocontainer.org</a>

          , 
          <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org">
          jakarta.apache.org</a>

          and 
          <a href="http://savannah.gnu.org">savannah.gnu.org</a>
          </li>

          <li><a href="http://www.collab.net/products/sd/version.html">SourceCast</a> 1.0 on 
          <a href="http://www.netbeans.org">www.netbeans.org</a>
          </li>

          <li><a href="http://www.collab.net/products/sd/version.html">SourceCast</a> 2.0 on 
          <a href="http://dev.java.net">dev.java.net</a>
          </li>

          <li><a href="http://www.freebsd.org/projects/cvsweb.html">CvsWeb</a> 1.0 on 
          <a href="http://dev.w3.org/cvsweb/">dev.w3.org</a>
          </li>
          
          <li><a href="http://www.freebsd.org/projects/cvsweb.html">CvsWeb</a> 2.0 on 
          <a href="http://www.kde.org/">www.kde.org</a>
          </li>
          
          <li><a href="http://www.horde.org/chora/">Chora</a> 2.0-dev on 
              <a href="http://cvs.php.net/">cvs.php.net</a>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </p>
    </section> 

    <section name="Quotes">
      <p>
        I was searching for a way to download CVS modules from behind a really
        strict firewall (and a very unhelpful IT staff). Thanks for making
        CVSGrab. It's really useful and needed. <br/>
        It worked first try for me. The examples are great, everything I need to
        know. <br/>
        James.       
      </p>
      <p>
        They talk about cvsgrab: <br/>
        <a href="http://www.gnomebangalore.org/?q=node/view/436">Madan's blog on GNOME Bangalore</a>
      </p>

      <p>Author: Ludovic Claude ( 
      <a href="mailto:ludovicc at users.sourceforge.net">email</a>

      ), freelance developer</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>

